const e="english",a=200,o=80,t=[{id:1374,question:"Okibe was rusticated for his [derogatory] remark about the principal",option:{a:"complimentary",b:"unwarranted",c:"lack luster",d:"unsavoury"},section:"Choose the one nearest in meaning to the word(s) in bracket",image:"",answer:"d",solution:`Derogatory; means showing a critical or disrespectful attitude.

Unsavoury; means unpleasant or morally offensive, the most suitable synonym for derogatory in this regard.

 `,examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:1,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1375,question:"Some men will continue to cause offences until they are given [a taste of their own medicine]",option:{a:"placated",b:"revenged on",c:"cured",d:"recompensed for"},section:"Choose the one nearest in meaning to the word(s) in bracket",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"Recompensed for is the correct answer. To have 'a taste of your own medicine' is to have the same unpleasant experience that one has caused another.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:2,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1376,question:"Justice is difficult to enforce because people are unwilling to accept any loss of [sovereignty]",option:{a:"positing",b:"leadership",c:"autonomy",d:"kingdom"},section:"Choose the one nearest in meaning to the word(s) in bracket",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Autonomy is the correct answer. Sovereignty means a situation of self-sufficiency and self-governance.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:3,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1377,question:"His many years of success in legal practice, .............. , didn't come out without challenges",option:{a:"but",b:"in spite of all",c:"indeed",d:"However"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"However is used when trying to include a new point, or buttress an old one with a comparison",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:4,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1378,question:`Choose the word that has the same rhyme 

Thyme`,option:{a:"climb",b:"bind",c:"time",d:"lime"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Time' sounds approximately the same way when pronounced as 'Thyme'",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:5,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1379,question:"There are still [virtuous] women in our society today",option:{a:"devilish",b:"clever",c:"intelligent",d:"upright"},section:"Choose the one nearest in meaning to the word(s) in bracket",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"Upright is correct answer. Virtuous means having and demonstrating high level of moral standards or ethics, which is the same as being upright,",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:6,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1380,question:"This type of response is [typical] of a lazy teacher",option:{a:"symptomatic",b:"characteristics",c:"universal",d:"incontestable"},section:"Choose the one nearest in meaning to the word(s) in bracket",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Characteristic is correct answer. A thing is described as 'typical' of something else when becomes an observable and noticeable quality or attribute of it.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:7,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1381,question:"Orthop[ae]dic",option:{a:"elite",b:"impasse",c:"cacophony",d:"sharp"},section:`Choose the word with the same vowel sound as the one in bracket
`,image:"",answer:"a",solution:"Elite is the correct answer. The vowel /i:/ pronounced as 'eee' (as in letter E e.g. tea) sound is present",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:8,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1382,question:"Band[a]ge",option:{a:"kite",b:"says",c:"cacophony",d:"cage"},section:`Choose the word with the same vowel sound as the one in bracket
`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Bandage' is pronounced as /bandɪdʒ/ with the [a] in bandage having the 'i' vowel sound, and option C 'cacophony' has the same vowel sound as with the letter 'y'. ",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:9,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1398,question:"The significance of Mr Bello's advice to Aliya on Bobo's gift is that",option:{a:" the gift is a demonstration of love and affection",b:"the gift shouldn't necessarily impose an obligation on Aliya to act in tune with Bobo's interest",c:"one of the foundations of his marriage with Aliya's mother is through gifting",d:"once a boy gives a girl a gift it necessarily means that he has an interest in mind"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:`The significance of Mr Bello's advice is that the recipient of a gift shouldn't out of indebtedness feel obliged to act upon the gesture of the giver, as such doesn't necessarily mean true love and affection.

See page 5.`,examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:25,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1399,question:"Aliya although is born with a silver spoon, but she has no freedom to move around meet new people unlike other persons. This signals to the…",option:{a:"criticism of strict parenting",b:"irony of life",c:"essence of a child's exposure",d:" expectations of wealthy parents"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Aliya at age 12 envy of the girls hawking on the street and their freedom to move about as compared to her restriction to move about, eventhough she born into a comfortable home, significantly indicates the irony of life i.e no one has it all.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:26,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1400,question:'It may be argued that Chapter Two is titled, "The Drive" particularly because...?',option:{a:"of the social disparity between the rich and the poor which is unlikely to end",b:" Aliya's father drove her home from the boarding house",c:"it indicates the realities and experiences shared during Mr Bello's drive with Aliya",d:"it was the best atmosphere for Mr Bello to scold Aliya for her wrongdoings"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Readers must see through the meanings of words and titles beyond their ordinarily usage where necessary. Aliya's drive home by Mr Bello is relevant not because of the drive but especially because Mr Bello used the opportunity of the informal atmosphere to educate his daughter about sexual maturity and the realities of life pictured by the hawking girls and their aspiration to be great in life.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:27,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1401,question:"The fact that Aliya wanted to be a pilot, then a musician, a songwriter, doctor and later a lawyer points to the",option:{a:"need for parents to choose a befitting career for their children",b:"reason that only passion can define one's career",c:"indecision that comes with choosing a career at a tender age",d:"need for schools to make their syllabus career based"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"The youthfulness and ambition as well as confusion that comes with choosing a career is evident at every child's tender age. Parents should only guide their children as to the choice of their career based on passion and not on prospects of the course or career only.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:28,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1402,question:'"The Gandhi Test" indicates how',option:{a:" stubborn people act without thinking of public perception",b:" one should act when it comes to choosing a career",c:" a child should make wise decisions mindless of popular thinking",d:" a person can make morally right decisions"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"Test is that 'you can tell if what you're doing is good or bad, if you want other people to know about it' which means that one should act and be mindful that people are watching.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:29,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1403,question:"Bobo proved Mr Bello's advice on infatuation as right when he",option:{a:"presented a gift to Aliya",b:"flirts with other girls",c:" eventually left for Ireland without saying a word to Aliya",d:"proclaimed his love for Aliya"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"The fact that Bobo later travelled to Ireland without even informing Aliya finally and undoubtedly cements Mr Bello's advice that his love for her was temporary.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:30,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1404,question:"The writer tried to point out religious intolerance in his book, by",option:{a:"discussing how the society believes certain religion is better than others",b:"using one of Aliya's classmates to condemn her religion",c:" demonstrating how the religious institutions forcefully impose their beliefs on the people",d:"painting Islam as a more righteous religion than others"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Rebecca's remark about Muslims going to hell because they are Non-Christians and because they kill people is a stereotypical misconception of religious intolerance as indicated in the text by the writer",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:31,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1405,question:"... is quick to anger and doesn't hide it when she is",option:{a:"Aliyu",b:"Mrs Bello",c:" Mr Bello",d:"Bobo"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Mrs Bello doesn't hide her anger whenever she is, she outter speaks her mind on the issue. Although she may not agree with her husband on something, she supports him however.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:32,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1406,question:"Aliya's choice of wanting to study medicine …",option:{a:"simply reflects her childishness",b:" indicates her affection for humanity",c:"is born out of the prospects of the course",d:"is primarily because of her father"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Aliya's interest in medicine was just so that she could help asthmatic children in the nearest future by donating inhalers to schools.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:33,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1407,question:"Mr Bello's best advice to Aliya on dating is that",option:{a:"gifting doesn't mean true affection",b:" dating can be so distracting",c:"she should wait for the right time",d:"she should never be committed to anyone"},section:`<b>Questions are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Seeing as dating is a challenging adventure even for adults, Aliya is advised to thread softly.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:34,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1408,question:"He was both a writer and a politician, but he was better ........ a singer",option:{a:"As if",b:"Like",c:"As",d:"to be"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:'The adverb "as" is the most suitable answer here to govern the noun phrase "a singer".',examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:35,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1409,question:"Vacancies in the company will be notified by .....",option:{a:"Bulletin",b:"Publication",c:"Publicity",d:"advertisement"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"Apparently, advertisement is the most viable means by which a company publicize vacancy ",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:36,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1410,question:"The driver was short of petrol, so he ........ down the road with the engine switched off",option:{a:"glided",b:"coasted",c:"wheeled",d:"taxied"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Coasted means to move forward in a vehicle without using the engine.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:37,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1411,question:"He started his career as an ........ Teacher",option:{a:"auxilary",b:"auxilliary",c:"auxiliary",d:"auxillary"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:'Auxiliary being an adjective to the noun "teacher" indicates providing supplementary or extra help, support or assistance.',examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:38,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1412,question:"Jide couldn't have said that. This means that Jide",option:{a:"ought not say that",b:"will not say that",c:" it's not likely jide said it",d:"Jide didn't say it"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:`"Couldn't have" here indicates the impossibility that Jide said it at all i.e it is rather unlikely for Jide to have said it.`,examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:39,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1413,question:"Bolu shall be the M.C. This means that",option:{a:"Bolu may be the M.C",b:"no one else will be the M.C",c:"later in life, Bolu will become an M.C",d:"Bolu may not be the M.C"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Shall' indicates a future tense, also 'the M.C' indicates a specific qualification or title. It should be noted that the use of article  'a' is used when we mention something for the first time. However, 'the' is used when something is obvious",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:40,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1414,question:"Bridget denied that she wasn't there. This means that",option:{a:"She confessed that she wasn't there",b:"She owned up not to be there",c:"She maintained she was there",d:"She maintained she wasn't there"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:`Deny'' is to say that something is not true.

'that she wasn't there' is the accusation.

For Bridget to deny that she wasn't there, she is simply saying it is untrue to say she wasn't there.  Therefore, she was there.`,examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:41,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1415,question:"Hadn't it rained, it wouldn't have been so bad",option:{a:"It was so bad because it didn't rain",b:"it rained and so it wasn't bad",c:"it wasn't bad because it rained",d:"it rained and that made it so bad"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"The usage of the anomalous verb 'had' alongside with the negatives; 'not' and that in 'wouldn't' means that, it actually rained and that didn't make things good.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:42,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1416,question:"If he had spoken up, he wouldn't have been given. This means that",option:{a:" he spoke up and was given",b:"he wasn't given because he spoke up",c:" he didn't speak up and wasn't given",d:" he was given because he didn't speak up"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"The interpretation of the statement is that the speaker or person didn't speak up and so he was given.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:43,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1417,question:"The police officer looks <u>pudgy</u>",option:{a:"tall and lean",b:"short and slim",c:" short and fat",d:" tall and fat"},section:"Choose the one opposite in meaning to the word(s) underlined.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"Pudgy means someone that is short and fat or thick, the opposite of pudgy according the options is ''tall and lean''.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:44,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1418,question:"After the wedding, the wife became <u>anorexic</u>",option:{a:"obese",b:"melancholic",c:"excited",d:"skinny"},section:"Choose the one opposite in meaning to the word(s) underlined.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"To be anorexic means to have an eating disorder resulting to an abnormally low body weight. Consequently, the direct opposite herein, is to be obese or fat.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:45,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1419,question:"<u>Procrastination</u> is the enemy of progress",option:{a:"acceleration",b:"laziness",c:"hardwork",d:"tiredness"},section:"Choose the one opposite in meaning to the word(s) underlined.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"When someone doesn't procrastinate or postpone things unnecessarily for example out of laziness, then he or she accelerates the pace of the work required.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:46,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1420,question:"Chief Money-Miss-Road is a <u>sitting duck</u.",option:{a:"vulnerable",b:"invincible",c:"lazy",d:"quick-witted"},section:"Choose the one opposite in meaning to the word(s) underlined.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Invincible is the correct answer. To be a sitting duck means to be without any form of protection against an attack from an enemy or from danger.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:47,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1421,question:"I abhor a <u>traitor</u>",option:{a:"fallacious person",b:"reveler of secrets",c:"progressive element",d:"keeper of secrets"},section:"Choose the one opposite in meaning to the word(s) underlined.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:`A traitor is a person who betrays someone or something, such as a friend, cause, or principle. 
The option that is most nearly opposite in meaning to the underlined word is optic 'c' (keeper of secret). A traitor is no keeper of secrets, but rather a revealer of one.`,examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:48,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1422,question:`Choose the word with the same vowel sound as the one in bracket

Cacoph[o]ny`,option:{a:"Sole",b:"sun",c:"scissors",d:"comb"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"The vowel sound /∂/ here is perceivable in the syllable in block form, e.g. bro-thER. In the same vein, the 'OR' in 'scissors' has the same sound.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:49,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1423,question:"Non[ch]alant",option:{a:"television",b:"arch",c:"champagne",d:"chest"},section:"Choose the word that has the same consonant sound as the one in bracket",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Champagne is the correct answer. The /∫/ sound prevalent here is evidenced in the pronunciation of the 'SH' of 'shout' of which the 'CH' in Champagne belongs to.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:50,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1424,question:"Smoo[th]",option:{a:"worth",b:"wealthy",c:"brother",d:"dress"},section:"Choose the word that has the same consonant sound as the one in bracket",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Brother is the correct answer. The sound present here is pronounceable from the 'TH' in 'these' (not /d/ as in 'drug' or /∅/ as in 'thanks')",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:51,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1425,question:"Ask[ed]",option:{a:"whistle",b:"bed",c:"set",d:"Third"},section:"Choose the word that has the same consonant sound as the one in bracket",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Set is the correct answer. The sound /t/ as in 'tank' is present here.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:52,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1426,question:"Lo[s]e",option:{a:"loose",b:"sue",c:"refuse",d:"phones"},section:"Choose the word that has the same consonant sound as the one in bracket",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"phones' is the correct answer. The sound /z/ is pronounceable with the letter 's'",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:53,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1427,question:"Choose the word that has a different stress pattern",option:{a:"calender",b:"aloud",c:"mechanic",d:"convivial"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"Calender is the correct answer. The first syllable i.e the 'CA' of 'calender' is stressed while rest are stressed in their second syllables respectively.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:54,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1428,question:"Choose the word that has a different stress pattern",option:{a:"enlighten",b:"unwanted",c:"agitate",d:"Informal"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"The first syllable in 'agitate' is stressed, the other options are stressed differently",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:55,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1429,question:"Choose the word that has a different stress pattern",option:{a:"incinerator",b:"indicate",c:"increase",d:"euphemism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"Its second syllable is stressed unlike the rest of the options where the first syllable is stressed.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:56,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1430,question:`Choose the word that has the same rhyme scheme.

Dice`,option:{a:"mint",b:"rice",c:"fried",d:"case"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"The sound is obtainable in the pronunciation of 'dice' and 'rice'.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:57,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1431,question:"The traditional chief NARRATED the story to the children",option:{a:" the children heard the story from the traditional chief",b:" who narrated the story to the children",c:"the children could not listen to the story by the traditional chief",d:"did the chief hide the story from the children"},section:"In each of the questions, the word in capital letters has the emphatic stress, Choose the option to which the given sentence relates.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"By way of juxtaposition, and recurring emphatic importance, Did the chief hide the story from the children is the most preferred answer.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:58,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1432,question:"The ACCOUNTANT paid the workers july salary in september",option:{a:"when were the workers paid",b:"did the cashier pay the workers salary in september",c:"workers received their july salary in september",d:"the september salary was paid in july"},section:"In each of the questions, the word in capital letters has the emphatic stress, Choose the option to which the given sentence relates.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"In answering questions on emphatic stress,  the answer in direct reversal to the one in block form and that seeks to clearly restate and provoke the statement is the most suitable. This is why did the cashier pay the workers salary in september is right.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:59,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1433,question:`In each of the questions, the word in capital letters has the emphatic stress, Choose the option to which the given sentence relates.

The cat DEVOURED the rat`,option:{a:"did the rat devour the cat",b:" what devoured the rat",c:" did the cat pet the rat",d:"is this rat that the cat devoured"},section:"In each of the questions, the word in capital letters has the emphatic stress, Choose the option to which the given sentence relates.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Did the cat pet the rat is the correct answer. The same reasoning in the authoritative answer to Question 59 is also relevant here to support Option as the most suitable answer.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:60,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1449,question:"The stereotypical act in the book centres",option:{a:"terrorism",b:"religious intolerance",c:"food insecurity",d:"the lifestyle of a teenager"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Aliya asks her Dad if it is true that all Muslims are terrorists and that they all perish. Her father corrects this stereotypical notion or unfounded generalised belief of some members of the society as regards their religion.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:76,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1450,question:"The novel places emphasis on the",option:{a:"need for strict parenting and schooling for children",b:" social disparity between the rich and the poor in the society",c:"relevance of bridging the communication gap between children and their parents",d:"abnormalities of the society and the confusion that comes with childishness"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"The writer appreciates the maintenance of close relationship between Aliya and her father. Her father was more or less her friend. This made for a fine balance of personal development for Aliya as her father guides her constantly on the realities of life, sexual maturity and exposition as well the need to excel in life.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:77,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1451,question:"Aliya was advised to be mindless of popular perception about her…",option:{a:"when it comes to her self esteem",b:" when it comes to applying",c:" whenever she is in love with anyone",d:"eventhough she craves for freedom like the hawking girls"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"a",solution:"Bunmi continously made jest of Aliya as fat, her father however, encouraged her (Aliya) to be proud of her body structure as beauty lies in the eyes of the beholder and not in what people ordinarily think.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:78,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1452,question:"In the novel, we learnt that",option:{a:"it pays to be diligent and hardworking",b:"beauty without character is nothing",c:"love and companionship are a no-go-area for teenagers",d:" one should follow the propagation of the media"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Among other things, Aliya's father emphasized that beauty is a relative word and as a matter of fact, beauty without good deeds is all vanity and worthless on the long run. As per dating, the advice is for teenagers to act patiently, this nullifies Option C.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:79,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1453,question:"Aliya's sixteenth birthday is special because",option:{a:"she receives birthday cards from her father every year since age twelve",b:"she was already matured to fully understand the realities of life stories told by her father",c:" her father gave her a birthday card and a digital camera",d:"of her father's sixteen-page letter detailing her life journey thus far"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"The specialty in Aliya's sixteenth birthday is a result of the sixteen-page letter which her father wrote to her, dedicating each page to each year of her life.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:80,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1454,question:"As it relates to sex education, Aliya's father advised that",option:{a:" she should abstain totally from sex as this is the worst sin ever in the history of human civilisation",b:"she should wisely decide before letting go of her body",c:"she should be mindful of her company of friends and the media's influence on sexual affairs",d:"sexual affair is no longer a hidden issue and she should wisely make her choices"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Mr Bello warned Aliya to be careful as regarding the kind of movies, books and progammes she entertain as well the company of friends she keeps.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:81,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1455,question:"Which one of the following critically relates to the novel's subject of concern",option:{a:"youthful ambition and confusion",b:"socialization",c:"religious bigotry",d:"the futility of life"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"The novelist placed emphatic importance on the value of home training and socialisation. This is exemplified in the information and communication gap between Aliya and her father.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:82,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1456,question:"A child's choice of career is a matter of",option:{a:"glamorous desire",b:"passion",c:" public perception as to the success rate and earnings of a profession",d:"parental discretion"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"The novelist noted that the choice of career of a child shouldn't be based on parental discretion as what is sellable and commands respect in the society but as to their child's interest in the course, with a bit of parental guidance.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:83,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1457,question:"The novelist noted that stereoscopic people should be",option:{a:" condemned for their bad thinking",b:" encouraged by admonition",c:"corrected of their bad thinking",d:" challenged to take up social responsibilities"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"The novelist acclaimed that stereoscopic persons are only victims of bad thinking and shouldn't be condemned in return for their ignorance. They should rather be corrected.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:84,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1458,question:"All in all, Aliya has …",option:{a:"the inheritance of her parents both in knowledge and assets",b:"been challenged to be exceptional in all her endeavors",c:" the responsibility to pass on the lessons of her father to her own children",d:" been portrayed as the definition of beauty and character"},section:`<b>Questions below are based on Bolaji Abdullahi's "Sweet Sixteen"</b>`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"The most important thing is not only for Aliya to abide by her father's advise built to as well lead such legacies for her children and the generations to come.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:85,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1459,question:"The employer, not the sales boy and his partner ........ responsible for the loss",option:{a:"are",b:"are being",c:"are never",d:"is"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"Going by the rule of concord, the phrase 'not his sales boy or his partner' is not part of the subject 'the employer'. Therefore, the singular verb should be used.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:86,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1460,question:"Both questions are alternatives; you answer ........ one ........ the other",option:{a:"either/or",b:"neither/nor",c:"either/nor",d:"neither/or"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"Option A is the best answer. Note that 'either' goes with 'or' and the usage of both creates an impression as to alternatives.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:87,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1461,question:"It is high time we ........ seeing her",option:{a:"stop",b:"will stop",c:"stopped",d:"stops"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"It is high time' suggests that something should be done and that it is already a bit late.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:88,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1462,question:"You can have ........ of these two books",option:{a:"either",b:"none",c:"any",d:"some"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"Either' is used when there is an alternative choice or decision to be made.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:89,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1463,question:"Either Buntu or you ........ to go",option:{a:"was",b:"are",c:"has",d:"is"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:`The rule of concord states an exception, that is when either or neither joins to subjects (one singular and the other plural)  the verb should be chosen by considering the nearer of the two subjects.

This means that if the second subject is plural the verb should be plural

'You' can take a plural form, therefore option B is the safest answer.`,examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:90,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1464,question:"The prisoner finally ........ that he drank to ........ on the night he committed the murder",option:{a:"acceded/access",b:"conceded/excess",c:"exceeded/extreme",d:"eluded/escape"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"To concede is to admit and the excessive drinking of the prisoner caused the murder.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:91,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1465,question:"I know my onions",option:{a:"I know my job very well",b:"I know my rights",c:"I am clever because of experience",d:"I am aware of my position"},section:"Choose the correct interpretations of the statement given, for the question",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"To know one's onions' is to be fully acquainted with a subject or the parctice in a field.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:92,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1466,question:`

America is the Mecca of the world`,option:{a:"America is the commercial garden of the world",b:"America is a beautiful place in the world",c:"America is a place where people like to visit",d:" America accepts assorted races throughout the world"},section:"Choose the correct interpretations of the statement given, for the question",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"The representative quality or title of Mecca indicates here that America is a sought after State by most people to visit",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:93,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1467,question:"All the Nigerian footballers have itchy feet",option:{a:"the footballers have insured feet",b:"the footballers use their feet to steer",c:"the footballers like to travel",d:"the footballers like play skillfully"},section:"Choose the correct interpretations of the statement given, for the question",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"The footballers like to travel is the best answer. 'Itchy' means not static, by implication.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:94,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1468,question:"Mr Santos Laliga is a [dipsomaniac]",option:{a:"teetotaler",b:"a drunkard",c:" an hater of women",d:" a promiscuous man"},section:`Choose the word that has an opposite meaning to the one in bracket for questions below.
`,image:"",answer:"a",solution:"A teetotaller is a person who never drinks alcohol, the antonym of a dipsomaniac.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:95,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1469,question:"The jollof rice served at the wedding reception was [malodorous]",option:{a:" small but palatable",b:" unpalatably big",c:"pleasant",d:"stale and smelly"},section:`Choose the word that has an opposite meaning to the one in bracket for questions below.
`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"Malodorous is an adjective for an odorous or unpleasant smell.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:96,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1470,question:"When it comes to playing the piano, I am a complete [ignoramus]",option:{a:"Idiot",b:"virtuoso",c:"novice",d:"nonentity"},section:`Choose the word that has an opposite meaning to the one in bracket for questions below.
`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"A virtuoso is an expert in a field while an ignoramus is a novice.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:97,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1471,question:"The [prodigious] building was razed to the carpet level yesterday",option:{a:"ramshackle",b:"modern",c:"colossal",d:"mini-sized"},section:`Choose the word that has an opposite meaning to the one in bracket for questions below.
`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"As 'prodigious' from the context of usage means big.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:98,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1472,question:"The sick man is now [ambulatory]",option:{a:"recovering gradually",b:"walking",c:" sound in health",d:"immobile"},section:`Choose the word that has an opposite meaning to the one in bracket for questions below.
`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"To ambulatory as in this context is to be able to move or walk around.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:99,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1473,question:"Every human being is [vulnerable] to communicable disease",option:{a:"liable",b:"lifted",c:"immune",d:"closed"},section:"CHOOSE THE OPTION THAT IS NEAREST IN MEANING TO THE WORD(S) IN BRACKET, FOR  THE QUESTIONS ",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"Vulnerability means here that one is open or susceptible to something. 'Liable' best fits this here.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:100,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1474,question:"The student's union leader delivered his speech [extempore]",option:{a:"out-of-hand",b:"accurately",c:"off the cuff",d:"courageously"},section:"CHOOSE THE OPTION THAT IS NEAREST IN MEANING TO THE WORD(S) IN BRACKET, FOR  THE QUESTIONS ",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"An extempore speech is made at the spur of the moment i.e without previous preparation.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:101,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1475,question:"These policies have been [espoused] by the ruling party",option:{a:"condemned",b:"rejected",c:"supported",d:"outlined"},section:"CHOOSE THE OPTION THAT IS NEAREST IN MEANING TO THE WORD(S) IN BRACKET, FOR  THE QUESTIONS ",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"To espouse is to adopt or support a belief or strategy.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:102,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1476,question:"Her findings [exploded] widely held beliefs about learning",option:{a:"challenged",b:"debunked",c:"projected",d:"confirmed"},section:"CHOOSE THE OPTION THAT IS NEAREST IN MEANING TO THE WORD(S) IN BRACKET, FOR  THE QUESTIONS ",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"Exploded as used in this context means to refute or criticise.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:103,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1477,question:`We must not [foreclose] reconciliation as the purpose of his trip
`,option:{a:"exclude",b:"consider",c:"underestimate",d:"forgo"},section:"CHOOSE THE OPTION THAT IS NEAREST IN MEANING TO THE WORD(S) IN BRACKET, FOR  THE QUESTIONS ",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"To foreclose is to leave out the consideration of an option or alternative to something.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:104,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1478,question:"G[ua]rantee",option:{a:"plait",b:"far",c:"guard",d:"aunt"},section:"Choose the word that has the same vowel sound as the one in bracket, from questions below",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"The vowel sound here is pronounceable in 'pat', 'apple' etc. Plait is the therefore the right answer.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:105,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1479,question:"B[oo]k",option:{a:"shoe",b:"group",c:"blue",d:"full"},section:"Choose the word that has the same vowel sound as the one in bracket, from questions below",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"The vowel sound obtainable here is the short /u/ sound as in 'put'. The rest of the options have elongated pronunciation than 'full'",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:106,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1480,question:"Neighb[our]",option:{a:"blood",b:"standard",c:"board",d:"source"},section:"Choose the word that has the same vowel sound as the one in bracket, from questions below",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"The vowel sound obtainable here is the /∂/ sound as in 'brother'. Stand[ar]d qualifies in this regard.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:107,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1481,question:"H[ei]r",option:{a:"Care",b:"Near",c:"mere",d:"weird"},section:"Choose the word that has the same vowel sound as the one in bracket, from questions below",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"The vowel sound here is /e∂/ which perceivable in 'Care', 'air'.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:108,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1482,question:"Ad[j]ust",option:{a:"Diary",b:"judge",c:"Dynasty",d:"Anticipate"},section:"Choose the word that has the same vowel sound as the one in bracket, from questions below",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"The sound obtainable here is evidenced in 'journey', 'gender'. Ju[d]ge has the consonant as these ones previously mentioned",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:109,hasPassage:0,category:"others"},{id:1483,question:"A[n]kle",option:{a:"Tongue",b:"New",c:"Pneumatic",d:"Photosynthesis"},section:"Choose the word that has the same vowel sound as the one in bracket, from questions below",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"The consonant sound obtainable here may be seen in 'gang', 'sing'. To[n]gue has the same consonant sound.",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019",questionNub:110,hasPassage:0,category:"others"}],s={subject:e,status:200,total:80,data:t};export{t as data,s as default,a as status,e as subject,o as total};
